<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!--
Created:       Fri Oct  2 12:47:06 2015 mstenber

-->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>

<?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<rfc
    ipr='trust200902'
    docName='draft-barth-homenet-wifi-roaming-00'
    category='exp'
    >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Homenet WiFi Roaming">
      Home Network WiFi Roaming
    </title>
    <author initials="S" surname="Barth" fullname="Steven Barth">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Halle</city>
          <code>06114</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cyrus@openwrt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2015" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Homenet Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Homenet</keyword>
    <keyword>DAD</keyword>
    <keyword>WiFi</keyword>
    <keyword>Roaming</keyword>
    <abstract>

      <t>This document describes a mechanism to manage host routes and
      statelessly proxy IPv6 Duplicate Address Detection messages between
      multiple WiFi links to allow client roaming.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>In a multi router home network it can be desirable to have a WiFi
      network accessible in different physical locations. Synchronization of
      configuration parameters like ESSID and authentication allows clients to
      seamlessly roam the network. However, a client switching from one WiFi
      AP to another might suffer from service disruption if each AP uses a
      different IP address prefix. To mitigate this issue, all AP links could
      be bridged on layer 2, which would lead to increased traffic on the home
      network backbone. This draft offers an alternative solutions based on
      host routing and proxying of Duplicate Address Detection for IPv6.</t>
      
      <t>In order to minimize additional complexity on routers, this draft
      either relies on existing state in the form the neighbor cache entries
      used for host routing or introduces only lightweight, stateless
      mechanism to distribute Duplicate Address Detection.</t>
      
      <t>However, an additional mechanism is needed to identify and share
      information about which routers have roaming interfaces, to which roaming
      interface set they belong, under which addresses these routers are
      reachable and which specific roaming prefixes are assigned. The specific
      mechanism is out of scope for this draft, however a solution based on
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-hncp" /> is conceivable.</t> 

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">


      <texttable suppress-title="true" style="none" align="left">
	<ttcol width="25%" /><ttcol width="75%" />

	<c>ESSID</c>
	<c>IEEE 802.11 Extended Service Set Identifier</c>

        <c /><c />
        
    <c>host route</c>
	<c>an IPv6 route with a prefix length of 128 intended to track a
	host on a roaming interface</c>

<c /><c />
        
    <c>roaming interface</c>
	<c>a network interface (typically IEEE 802.11) which shares an address
	prefix with other similar interfaces to allow seamless client roaming</c>

<c /><c />

    <c>roaming interface set</c>
	<c>the set of roaming interfaces which share a particular address
	prefix</c>

<c /><c />
        
    <c>roaming prefix</c>
	<c>an IPv6 address prefix shared between all interfaces in a roaming
	interface set</c>

<c /><c />

      </texttable>

      <section anchor="kwd" title='Requirements Language'>

        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
          be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'>RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>

	<section title="Stateless Duplicate Address Detection (DAD) Proxy">
		<t>Sharing a roaming prefix accross multiple separate interfaces might
		lead to address colissions between hosts on different interfaces of
		the same set. Therefore, it needs to be ensured that DAD messages are
		shared across interfaces. The typical DAD process involves the
		querying host sending one or more Neighbor Solicitations using the
		unspecified address as a source and any colliding host replying to the
		all-nodes address as specified in <xref target="RFC4862" /> and
		<xref target="RFC4861" />.</t>
		
		<section title="Receipt and Distribution of DAD Messages">
			<t>The following requirements apply for receiving DAD traffic
			on roaming interfaces:
			<list>
				<t>A router MUST listen for all Neighbor Solicitations with
				a target addresses from an assigned roaming prefix having the
				unspecified address as the source address. Similarly it MUST
				listen for all Neighbor Advertisements with a target address
				from an assigned roaming prefix and having the all-nodes
				multicast address as the destination address.</t>
				
				<t>A router MUST forward all such messages via global unicast
				to all other routers having roaming interfaces sharing the
				roaming prefixes the target address of the respective message
				belongs to.</t>
			
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Proxying forwarded of DAD Messages">
			<t>The following requirements apply to routers having roaming
			interfaces for receiving and proxying forwarded DAD traffic to
			clients on respective interfaces:
			<list>
				<t>A router MUST listen for Neighbor Solicitations and
				Advertisements sent via global unicast from other routers
				having roaming interfaces with the same roaming prefix.</t>
				
				<t>Upon reception of such a Neighbor Solicitation, the
				router MUST forward the message to all roaming interfaces
				having prefixes matching the target address. It MUST use
				the unspecified address as source and the respective solicited
				node multicast-address as destination address.</t>
				
				<t>Upon reception of such a Neighbor Advertisement, the
				router MUST forward the message to all roaming interfaces
				having prefixes matching the target address. It MUST use
				the all-nodes multicast-address as destination address.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
	</section>

  	<section title="Maintaining Host Routes">
  		<t>Host routes are necessary in order to unambiguously forward packets
  		to potentially roaming WiFi clients. This draft ties the announcement
  		of host routes to the presence of <xref target="RFC4861">Neighbor Cache
  		</xref> entries for addresses of roaming prefixes. The following
  		requirements apply:
  		
  		<list>
  			<t>A router MUST announce a host route for an IPv6 address belonging
  			to a roaming prefix whenever there is a corresponding entry for it
  			in the roaming interface's neighbor cache with the states
  			REACHABLE, STALE, DELAY or PROBE.</t>
  			
  			<t>A router MUST retract any host route for an IPv6 address 
  			immediately when a neighbor lookup for it has finally failed on the
  			roaming interface OR when a physical disconnect of the respective
  			client (e.g., a WiFi disassociation) has been noticed.</t>
  		
  			<t>A router SHOULD be able to manage and publish host routes for at
  			least two IPv6 addresses for every connected host and IPv6 roaming
  			prefix announced on a romaing interface.</t>
  			
  			<t>The router SHOULD NOT flush neighbor cache entries in STALE
  			state and respective host routes. Instead it SHOULD try to promote
  			STALE entries to REACHABLE and only upon failure remove the cache
  			entry and route. This ensures that the address is actually not used
  			anymore and the host does not happen to be merely temporarily
  			inactive and potentially waiting for incoming packets.</t>
  			
  		</list>
  		</t>
  	</section>
  	

    <section title="Roaming Interface Configuration">
      <t>The following requirements are suggested for interfaces intended
      to use the roaming features described in this draft:
      
      <list>      
      	<t>Router Advertisements SHOULD only include Prefix Information Options
      	for one more IPv6 roaming prefixes. Such Prefix Information Options
      	MUST have the A-Bit set and the L-Bit cleared.</t>
      	
      	<t>The IPv6 address fe80::1 SHOULD be used as fixed link-local address
      	exclusively by the router on roaming interfaces. This is to ensure
      	that the IPv6 default route for clients stays the same across roaming
      	interfaces. Furthermore the address SHOULD be announced as recursive
      	DNS server address should the router provide such a service.</t> 
      	
      	<t>Router Advertisements SHOULD be sent as described in <xref
      	target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-reducing-ra-energy-consumption" />.</t>
      	
      	<t>Stateful DHCPv6 MUST NOT be used to avoid the need to synchronize
      	lease information and relay DHCPv6 packets. Similary Router
      	Advertisements MUST be sent with the M-Bit cleared.</t>
      	
      	<t>NAT64 and DNS64 SHOULD be used if IPv4 connectivity is desired,
      	alternatively different and disjoint native IPv4 prefixes MAY be
      	used on each individual roaming interface.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
  	</section>
  	


    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>TBD</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>No action needed.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-v6ops-reducing-ra-energy-consumption-02"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-09"?>
    </references>
    
    <section title="Discussion Points [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>
    	<list style="symbols">
    	  <t>It is debatable which kind of transport could be used for the
    	  proxied DAD messages. Plain ICMPv6 could be possibly but might be
    	  dropped by certain hosts. Similarly UDP or DTLS encapsulation could
    	  be used easily if a port was allocated or exchanged.</t>
    	  
    	  <t>Is additional reliability useful and if so what kind? Normally
    	  hosts only send a single DAD solicitation, so the probability of
    	  a total packet loss increases with each forwarding hop. Trivially
    	  one could simply duplicate all proxied DAD messages or use TCP
    	  framing or SCTP. However the announced Retrans Timer value in the RA
    	  and retransmission parameters of the transport need to be adjusted,
    	  so that any resend and matching replies happen before the host
    	  considers the DAD process to have resulted in no colissions.</t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changelog [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>draft-barth-homenet-wifi-roaming-00:
      <list style="symbols">

        <t>Initial version.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Draft Source [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>As usual, this draft is available at <eref
      target="https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/">
      https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/</eref>
      in source format (with nice Makefile too). Feel free to send comments
      and/or pull requests if and when you have changes to it! </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t></t>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
