<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!--
Created:       Fri Oct  2 12:47:06 2015 mstenber

-->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>

<?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<rfc
    ipr='trust200902'
    docName='draft-stenberg-mif-mpvd-dns-00'
    category='std'
    >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPVD using DNS">
      Multiple Provisioning Domains using DNS
    </title>
    <author initials="M" surname="Stenberg" fullname="Markus Stenberg">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Helsinki</city>
          <code>00930</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>markus.stenberg@iki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Barth" fullname="Steven Barth">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Halle</city>
          <code>06114</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cyrus@openwrt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2015" />

    <area>TBD</area>
    <workgroup>MIF Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>PVD</keyword>
    <keyword>DNS</keyword>
    <abstract>
	<t>This document describes a mechanism to transmit and secure provisioning
	domain information for IPv6 and IPv4 addresses by using reverse DNS
	resolution. In addition it specifies backwards-compatible extensions to
	IPv6 host configuration to support special-purpose global IPv6 prefixes
	and routers which can only be used to access certain isolated services.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction"> 
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">

      <texttable suppress-title="true" style="none" align="left">
	<ttcol width="25%" /><ttcol width="75%" />

	<c>special-purpose IPv6 prefix</c>
	<c>a global IPv6 source prefix that cannot be used to reach the public
	IPv6 internet but instead only allows access to certain special services
	(e.g., a walled garden, VoIP, IPTV, ...).</c>

        <c /><c />

      </texttable>


      <section anchor="kwd" title='Requirements Language'>

        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
          be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'>RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Overview">

      <t>TBD</t>

    </section>
    
    <section anchor="recordtag" title="_pvd Record Tags">
    	<t>TODO</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="sp" title="Special-purpose IPv6 prefixes">
		<t>A service provider might wish to assign certain global unicast
		address prefixes which can be used to reach a limited set of services
		only. In the presence of legacy hosts it must be ensured however
		that these prefixes are not mistakenly used as source addresses for
		other destinations. This section therefore defines optional extensions
		to <xref target="RFC4861">NDP</xref>, <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6
		</xref> and <xref target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref> to indicate this
		state.</t>
		
		<section anchor="sp-slaac"
		  title="Extensions to Stateless Address Autoconfiguration">
			<t><xref target="RFC4861">NDP</xref> defines the Prefix
			Information option to announce prefixes for stateless address
			configuration. The "A-bit" is set, whenever hosts may autonomously
			derive addresses from a given prefix. For special-purpose prefixes
			this document defines the first bit of the Reserved1-field as the
			"S-Bit".</t>
			
			<t>The following additional requirements apply to hosts intending
			to support global special-purpose IPv6 prefixes:
			<list>
				<t>Upon reception of a Prefix Information Option with the
				S-Bit set, it should behave as if the A-Bit was set, however
				(unless the A-Bit was actually set by the sending router)
				it MUST delay using any adresses derived from the prefix
				until it has queried, retrieved and honored (see TODO)
				at least all mandatory provisioning domain information related
				to the given prefix.</t>
				
				<t>A host SHOULD NOT interpretate the S-Bit being clear as an
				indicator that no provisioning domain information is available
				for a given prefix.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
			
			<t>
			The following additional requirements apply to routers:
			<list>
				<t>A router MUST NOT set the A-Bit for global unicast
				address prefixes which cannot be used to reach the public
				IPv6 internet.</t>
			
				<t>A router SHOULD use the S-Bit to indicate that PVD-aware
				hosts can statelessly assign themselves addresses from a given
				prefix. It MAY use the S-Bit in addition to the A-Bit to
				indicate that a prefix usable to reach the public IPv6
				internet has additional (optional) provisioning domain
				information.</t>
				
				<t>A router announcing one or more Prefix Information options
				with the S-Bit set MUST also announce one or more recursive
				DNS servers using a <xref target="RFC6106">Recursive DNS Server
				Option</xref>. If none of the Prefix Information Options it
				announces have the A-Bit set then at least one of these
				recursive DNS servers MUST be reachable using a link-local
				address.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="sp-dhcpv6" title="Extensions to DHCPv6">
		  <t>Using <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref> and <xref
		  target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref> servers can actively decide which
		  addresses or prefixes are assigned to clients and requesting routers,
		  however a mechanism is needed to distinguish PVD-aware devices and
		  in the same sense PVD-aware devices need to be able to detect which
		  prefixes and addresses are special-purpose. Therefore, a zero-length
		  DHCPv6 option OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE is defined to be added as a
		  suboption to OPTION_IAADDR and OPTION_IAPREFIX options.</t>
		  
		  <t>The following additional requirements apply to clients and
		  requesting routers intending to support global special-purpose IPv6
		  prefixes via DHCPv6:
		  <list>
		  	<t>A client or requesting router MUST include the option code
		  	OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE in an option OPTION_ORO in its SOLICIT and
		  	REQUEST messages, whenever it wishes to accept special-purpose
		  	prefixes in its identity associations.</t>
		  	
		  	<t>Upon reception of an OPTION_IAADDR or OPTION_IAPREFIX option
		  	having an embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option it MUST delay
		  	using any adresses derived from the prefix as source address for
		  	its own communication until it has queried, retrieved and
		  	honored (see TODO) at least all mandatory provisioning domain
		  	information related to the given prefix or address. If it is a
		  	requesting router, it MAY however subdelegate prefixes or assign
		  	addresses from special-purpose prefixes to clients without doing
		  	so as long as the requirements in the following paragraph are
		  	honored.</t> 
		  </list>
		  </t>
		  
		  <t>The following additional requirements apply to routers assigning
		  addresses from or delegating (parts of) special-purpose prefixes
		  using DHCPv6:
		  <list>
		  	<t>A router MUST include a zero-length suboption of type
		  	OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE in every OPTION_IAADDR and OPTION_IAPREFIX
		  	option it assings or delegates containing a global unicast address
		  	or prefix which cannot be used to reach the public IPv6 internet.
		  	It MUST NOT assign or delegate such an address or prefix to a
		  	client or requesting router not including the option code of
		  	OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE inside an OPTION_ORO option.</t>
		  	
		  	<t>A router announcing one or more addresses or prefixes
			with an embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option MUST also announce
			one or more recursive DNS servers using a <xref target="RFC3646">
			OPTION_DNS_SERVERS option</xref>. If all of the addresses in a
			DHCPv6 reply carry the embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option
			then at least one of the announced recursive DNS servers MUST
			be reachable using a link-local address.</t>
		  </list>
		  </t>
		</section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

		<t>Security properties of NDP and DHCPv6 are inherited for the
		respective extensions, therefore relevant sections of <xref
		target="RFC4861" /> and <xref target="RFC3315" /> should be consulted.
		In any case, signalling addresses and prefixes to be special-purpose
		does not have a significant impact on the underlying assignment and
		delegation mechanisms.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

		<t>IANA is requested to setup a _pvd DNS TXT Record Tag registry
		with a default policy of <xref target="RFC5226">RFC Required</xref>
		and the following initial contents (see <xref target="recordtag" />):
		</t>

		<t>This document defines a new bit for the NDP Prefix Information
		Option (the S-bit). There is currently no registration procedure for
		such bits, so IANA should not take any action on this matter.</t>
      
		<t>IANA should assign a DHCPv6 option code OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE to
		the DHCPv6 option code space defined in <xref target="RFC3315" />.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6763.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2308.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3646.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6106.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>
    </references>
    <!--<references title="Informative references">
      
    </references>-->

    <section title="This solution compared to doing this in DHCPv6/NDP [RFC
                    Editor: please remove]">

      <t>The angle of attack of the MIF work to date (autumn 2015) has been
      to add container options and their transfer mechanisms to DHCPv6 and
      NDP. This document details a different approach, and therefore it is
      sensible to compare it to to the existing solutions in terms of
      (highly subjective) pros and cons.

      The authors consider pros of this proposal to be:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>No overhead for hosts that do not care (possibly most; no
        spurious RA options, ...)</t>

        <t>No problems with relaying data; if the first-hop device does not
        care, DNS request propagate onwards.</t>

        <t>Little/no changes to DHCP, DHCPv6, DHCPv6-PD or RA.</t>

        <t>No duplication of specifications / TLVs for DHCP, DHCPv6 and
        RA.</t>

        <t>Solves m:n prefix &lt;-&gt; PVD elegantly: no need to either
        duplicate applying prefix for each PVD or duplicate each PVD for
        each applying prefix.</t>

        <t>Easily extensible (TXT records, no TLV definitions, parsing and
        generation necessary)</t>

        <t>Probably not affected by IPR on draft-ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support</t>

        <t>Reuses the existing reverse DNS infrastructure</t>
      </list>

      The authors consider cons of this proposal to be:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>This scheme requires DNS servers ‘close’ on the path to the
        user, if changed information is to be sent; otherwise centralized
        solution would work (with some synthesized records).</t>

        <t>Security using either DNSSec or in-band hashes is rather painful
        (but possibly not more than the scheme in the current DHCP/RA
        drafts), so the default would most likely be insecure. That is not
        much different from DHCP*/RA, which are also 99.999…% of the time
        not secured.</t>

      </list>

      </t>

    </section>
 
    <section title="Discussion Points [RFC Editor: please remove]">
    	<t>
    	<list style="symbols">
    	<t>Besides special purpose prefixes, it might be desirable to
    	have special purpose routers which only provide access to certain
    	services but not the entire internet. These services could be
    	announced by only using more-specific routes, however if the
    	destination addresses are possibly changing, extension of the RIO
    	mechanism might be needed. One possibility would be to add a new
    	RIO S-flag with semantics like: "When the host receives
    	a Route Information Option with the S-Bit set, it MUST ignore the value
    	in the Prf-field (even if it is (10)) and instead assume the preference
    	to have a value greater than (11). However, it MUST only use the route
    	for packets having a source prefix announced by the same router.". This
    	would allow selective routes (Prf=(10)) only applying to MIF-hosts.</t>
    	
        <t>DNSSEC delegation of reverse zones might be difficult in some cases.
        It is debatable, whether we want a complementary in-band signing
        mechanism as well, e.g., pre-shared public keys associated the domain
        name of the TXT records and "sig-X=..." record tags (where X identifies
        the specific key) and ... is an EdDSA or ECDSA signature over all
        records not starting with "sig-". Care would need to be taken wrt. TTL
        and negative caching though.</t>
		</list>
		</t>
	</section>


    <section title="Changelog [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>draft-stenberg-mif-mpvd-dns-00:
      <list style="symbols">

        <t>Initial version.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Draft Source [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>As usual, this draft is available at <eref
      target="https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/">
      https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/</eref>
      in source format (with nice Makefile too). Feel free to send comments
      and/or pull requests if and when you have changes to it! </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>Thanks to Eric Vyncke for the original idea of using DNS for
      transmitting PVD information.</t>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
