<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!--
Created:       Mon Nov 18 17:55:22 2013 mstenber

split from draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-03-pre - homenet specific ones


TBD:

- A lot of RFCs seem to assume DHCP = DHCPv4. Perhaps define the fact
somewhere that DHCP = DHCPv4+DHCPv6 here?
[SB] should be unambiguous now, if not please mark single occurences where it isn't
[MSt] it is now. some initial definition would still be nice ;)

- Announce <> publish term bit mixed; hmm
[SB] is that problematic? what is the "genuine" term?
[MSt] Not really problematic I think, just makes it potentially harder to
read for someone not initiated to this stuff. There are some cases where
'announce' is only valid verb though in the current text, and TLVs are typically
published/originated/whatever in the link-state literature. (Mostly to
indicate that they persist for long period of time, as opposed just to
announce, which by definition is only transient occurrence. Why the hell am
I writing an essay on this. :-p)

-->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>

<?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<rfc
    ipr='trust200902'
    docName='draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-06'
    category='std'
    >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Home Networking Control Protocol">
      Home Networking Control Protocol
    </title>
    <author initials="M" surname="Stenberg" fullname="Markus Stenberg">
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Helsinki</city>
          <code>00930</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>markus.stenberg@iki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Barth" fullname="Steven Barth">
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Halle</city>
          <code>06114</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cyrus@openwrt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="P" surname="Pfister" fullname="Pierre Pfister">
        <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street/>
                <city>Paris</city>
                <country>France</country>
            </postal>
            <email>pierre.pfister@darou.fr</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2015" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Homenet Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>Homenet</keyword>
    <keyword>DNCP</keyword>
    <abstract>

      <t>This document describes the Home Networking Control Protocol
      (HNCP), an extensible configuration protocol and a set of requirements
      for home network devices on top of the Distributed Node Consensus
      Protocol (DNCP). It enables automated configuration of addresses, naming,
      network borders and the seamless use of a routing protocol.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>HNCP synchronizes state across a small site
      in order to allow automated network configuration.
      The protocol enables use of border discovery, address prefix
      distribution <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-prefix-assignment" />,
      naming and other services across multiple links.</t>

      <t>HNCP provides enough information for a routing protocol to operate
      without homenet-specific extensions. In homenet environments where
      multiple IPv6 source-prefixes can be present, routing based on source
      and destination address is necessary <xref target="RFC7368" />.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="kwd" title='Requirements language'>

      <t>
       The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
       NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
       RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
       be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'>RFC 2119</xref>.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="DNCP Profile">
      <t>HNCP is defined as a profile of <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-dncp">
      DNCP</xref> with the following parameters:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>HNCP uses UDP datagrams on port HNCP-UDP-PORT as a transport
        over link-local scoped IPv6, using unicast and multicast
        (All-Homenet-Routers is the HNCP group address).
        Received datagrams with an IPv6 source or
        destination address which is not link-local scoped MUST be
        ignored. Each node MUST be able to receive (and potentially reassemble)
	UDP datagrams with a payload of at least 4000 bytes.</t>

        <t>HNCP operates on multicast-capable interfaces only. HNCP routers
        MUST assign a unique 32-bit endpoint identifier to each
        interface for which HNCP is enabled. The value zero is reserved
        for internal purposes.
        Implementations MAY use a value equivalent to the sin6_scope_id for
        the given interface.</t>

        <t>HNCP unicast traffic SHOULD be secured using <xref
        target="RFC6347">DTLS</xref> as described in DNCP if exchanged over
        unsecured links. UDP on port HNCP-DTLS-PORT is used for this
        purpose.  A node implementing HNCP security MUST support
        the DNCP Pre-Shared Key method, SHOULD support the DNCP Certificate
        Based Trust Consensus and MAY support the PKI-based trust
        method.</t>

        <t>HNCP uses opaque 32-bit node identifiers
        (DNCP_NODE_IDENTIFIER_LENGTH = 32). A node implementing HNCP SHOULD
        generate and use a random node identifier. If using a random node
        identifier and there is a node identifier collision, the node MUST
        immediately generate and use a new random node identifier which is
        not used by any other node.</t>

        <t>HNCP nodes MUST ignore all Node State TLVs received via
        multicast on a link which has DNCP security enabled in order
        to prevent spoofing of node state changes.</t>

        <t>HNCP nodes use the following Trickle parameters:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>k SHOULD be 1, as the timer reset when data is updated and
          further retransmissions should handle packet loss.</t>

          <t>Imin SHOULD be 200 milliseconds but MUST NOT be lower.
          Note: Earliest transmissions may occur at Imin / 2.</t>

          <t>Imax SHOULD be 7 doublings of Imin (i.e. 25.6 seconds)
          but MUST NOT be lower.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>HNCP nodes MUST use the leading 64 bits of <xref
        target="RFC1321">MD5</xref> as DNCP non-cryptographic hash function
        H(x).</t>

        <t>HNCP nodes MUST use DNCP's keep-alive extension on all endpoints.
        The following parameters are suggested:
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>Default keep-alive interval (DNCP_KEEPALIVE_INTERVAL): 20 seconds.</t>
            <t>Multiplier (DNCP_KEEPALIVE_MULTIPLIER): 2.1.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Common Links" anchor="links">

      <t>HNCP uses the concept of Common Links for some of its
      applications. A Common Link usually refers to a link layer broadcast
      domain with certain properties and is used, e.g., to determine where
      prefixes should be assigned or which neighboring nodes
      participate in the election of a DHCP(v6) server.
      The Common Link is computed separately for each local
      interface, and it always contains the local interface. Additionally,
      if the local interface is not in ad-hoc mode, it also contains the
      set of interfaces that are bidirectionally reachable from the given
      local interface, i.e. every remote interface of a remote node meeting
      all of the following requirements:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>The local node publishes a Neighbor TLV with:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Neighbor Node Identifier = remote node's node identifier</t>

          <t>Neighbor Endpoint Identifier = remote interface's endpoint
          identifier</t>

          <t>Endpoint Identifier = local interface's endpoint identifier</t>

        </list>
        </t>

        <t>The remote node publishes a Neighbor TLV with:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Neighbor Node Identifier = local node's node identifier</t>

          <t>Neighbor Endpoint Identifier = local interface's endpoint
          identifier</t>

          <t>Endpoint Identifier = remote interface's endpoint identifier</t>

        </list>
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>A node MUST be able to detect whether two of its local interfaces are
      connected, e.g. by detecting an identical remote interface
      being part of the Common Links of both local interfaces.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Border Discovery" anchor="bd">

      <t>HNCP router's interfaces are either internal, external or of a different
          category derived from the internal one.
          This section defines the border discovery algorithm.
          It is suitable for both IPv4 and IPv6 (single or dual-stack) and
          determines whether an HNCP interface is internal, external,
          or uses another fixed category. The algorithm is derived from the
          edge router interactions described in the
          <xref target="RFC7084">Basic Requirements for IPv6 Customer Edge
              Routers</xref>.  This algorithm
          MUST be implemented by any router implementing HNCP.</t>

    <t>The border discovery auto-detection algorithm works as follows,
    with evaluation stopping at first match:
    <list style="numbers">
        <t>If a fixed category is configured for the interface, it MUST be used.</t>

        <t>If a delegated prefix could be acquired by running a DHCPv6
            client on the interface, it MUST be considered external.</t>

        <t>If an IPv4 address could be acquired by running a DHCPv4 client
            on the interface it MUST be considered external.</t>

        <t>Otherwise the interface MUST be considered internal.</t>
    </list>
    </t>

      <t>In order to avoid conflicts between border discovery and HNCP
      routers running <xref target="RFC2131">DHCPv4</xref> or <xref
      target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref> servers, each router MUST implement
      the following mechanism based on <xref target="RFC3004">The User
      Class Option for DHCPv4</xref> and its <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6
      counterpart</xref>:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>An HNCP router running a DHCP client on an HNCP interface
        MUST include a DHCP User-Class consisting of the ASCII-String
        "HOMENET".</t>

        <t>An HNCP router running a DHCP server on an HNCP interface
        MUST ignore or reject DHCP-Requests containing a DHCP User-Class
        consisting of the ASCII-String "HOMENET".</t>

      </list>
      </t>

      <t>A router MUST allow setting a category of either auto-detected,
      internal or external for each interface which is suitable for both
      internal and external connections. In addition the following
      specializations of the internal category are defined to modify the
      local router behavior:

      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Leaf category:"> This declares an interface used by
        client devices only. Such an interface acts as an internal interface
        with the exception that HNCP or routing protocol traffic MUST NOT be sent
        on the interface, and all such traffic received on the interface MUST be ignored.
        This category SHOULD be supported.</t>

        <t hangText="Guest category:"> This declares an interface used by
        untrusted client devices only. In addition to the restrictions of
        the Leaf category, HNCP routers MUST enable firewalling rules such that
        connected devices are unable to reach other
        devices inside the HNCP network or query services advertised by them
        unless explicitly allowed. This category SHOULD be supported.</t>

        <t hangText="Ad-hoc category:"> This configures an interface to be
        <xref target="links">ad-hoc</xref>. Ad-hoc interfaces are considered internal but no
        assumption is made on the the link transitivity properties.
        Support for this category is OPTIONAL.</t>

        <t hangText="Hybrid category:"> This declares an interface to
        be internal while still running DHCPv4 and DHCPv6-PD clients on it. It
        is assumed that the link is under control of a legacy, trustworthy
        non-HNCP router, still within the same network. Detection of this
        category automatically in addition to manual configuration is
        out of scope of this document. Support for this category is OPTIONAL.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>Each router MUST continuously scan each active interface that does
      not have a fixed category in order to dynamically reclassify it if
      necessary.  The router therefore runs an appropriately configured
      DHCPv4 and DHCPv6 client as long as the interface is active including
      states where it considers the interface to be internal. The router
      SHOULD wait for a reasonable time period (5 seconds as a default),
      during which the DHCP clients can acquire a lease, before
      treating a newly activated or previously external interface as
      internal. Once it treats a certain interface as internal it MUST
      start forwarding traffic with appropriate source addresses between
      its internal interfaces and allow internal traffic to reach external
      networks according to the routes it publishes.
      Once a router detects an interface transitioning to external it MUST
      stop any previously enabled internal forwarding. In addition it
      SHOULD announce the acquired information for use in the network as
      described in later sections of this draft if the interface appears to
      be connected to an external network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Autonomic Address Configuration">
      <t>This section specifies how HNCP routers configure host and router
      addresses. At first border routers share information obtained from
      service providers or local configuration by publishing one or more
      External Connection TLVs. These contain other TLVs such as Delegated
      Prefix TLVs which are then used for prefix assignment. Finally, HNCP
      routers obtain addresses using a stateless (SLAAC-like) procedure or a
      specific stateful mechanism and hosts and legacy routers are configured
      using SLAAC or DHCP.</t>

      <t>In all TLVs specified in this section which include a prefix, IPv4 prefixes
      are encoded using the <xref target="RFC4291">IPv4-mapped IPv6 addresses format</xref>.
      The prefix length of such IPv4 prefix is set to 96 plus the IPv4 prefix length.</t>

      <section title="External Connections">
        <t>Each HNCP router MAY obtain external connection information from
        one or more sources, e.g., <xref target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref>,
        <xref target="RFC6241">NETCONF</xref> or static configuration. This
        section specifies how such information is encoded and advertised.</t>

        <section title="External Connection TLV">
          <t>An External Connection TLV is a container-TLV used to
          gather network configuration information associated with
          a single external connection. A node MAY publish an arbitrary
          number of instances of this TLV.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type: EXTERNAL-CONNECTION (33)|             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                          Nested TLVs                          |
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The External Connection TLV is a container which:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>MAY contain an arbitrary number of Delegated Prefix TLVs.</t>
              <t>MUST NOT contain multiple Delegated Prefix TLVs with identical or
                  overlapping prefixes. In such a situation, the External Connection TLV MUST be ignored.</t>
              <t>MAY contain at most one DHCPv6 Data TLV and at most one
              DHCPv4 Data TLV encoding options associated with the External
              Connection but MUST NOT contain more than one of each otherwise
              the External Connection TLV MUST be ignored.</t>
              <t>MAY contain other TLVs for future use.
                  Such additional TLVs MUST be ignored.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>

        <section title="Delegated Prefix TLV">
          <t>The Delegated Prefix TLV is used by HNCP routers to advertise
          prefixes which are allocated to the whole network and will be used
          for prefix assignment. Any Delegated Prefix TLV MUST be nested
          in an External Connection TLV.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type: DELEGATED-PREFIX (34)  |          Length: >= 9         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Valid Lifetime                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Preferred Lifetime                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Prefix Length |                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+            Prefix [+ nested TLVs]             +
|                                                               |
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Valid Lifetime: ">The time in seconds the delegated
              prefix is valid. The value is relative to the point in time the
              Node-Data TLV was last published. It MUST be updated whenever
              the node republishes its Node-Data TLV.</t>

              <t hangText="Preferred Lifetime: ">The time in seconds the
              delegated prefix is preferred. The value is relative to the
              point in time the Node-Data TLV was last published. It MUST be
              updated whenever the node republishes its Node-Data TLV.</t>

              <t hangText="Prefix Length: ">The number of significant bits in
              the Prefix.</t>

              <t hangText="Prefix: ">Significant bits of the prefix padded
              with zeroes up to the next byte boundary.</t>

              <t hangText="Nested TLVs:">Other TLVs included in the Delegated
              Prefix TLV and starting at the next 32-bit boundary following
              the end of the encoded prefix:

                <list style="symbols">
                  <t>Zero or more Prefix Domain TLVs. In absence of any such
                  TLV the prefix is assumed to be generated by an HNCP-router
                  and for internal use only.</t>

                  <t>If the encoded prefix represents an IPv6 prefix, at
                  most one DHCPv6 Data TLV MAY be included, and any included
                      DHCPv4 Data TLV MUST be ignored.</t>

                  <t>If the prefix represents an IPv4 prefix (encoded as an IPv4-mapped IPv6 prefix),
                      at most one DHCPv4 Data TLV MAY be
                  included, and any included DHCPv6 Data TLV MUST be ignored.</t>

                  <t>It MAY contain other TLVs for future use.
                      Such additional TLVs MUST be ignored.</t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

		<section title="Prefix Domain TLV">
          <t>The Prefix Domain TLV contains information about the origin and
          applicability of a delegated prefix. This information can be used
          to determine whether prefixes for a certain domain (e.g. local
          reachability, internet connectivity) do exist or should be acquired
          and to make decisions about assigning prefixes to certain links or
          to fine-tune border firewalls.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: PREFIX-DOMAIN (43)   |          Length: >= 1         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Domain Type  |                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                   Domain ID                   +
|                                                               |
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Domain Type: ">The type of the domain identifier.
                <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="0      :">Internet connectivity
                      (domain ID is empty).</t>
                      <t hangText="1-128  :">Explicit destination prefix with the
                          Domain Type being the actual length of the prefix
                      (Domain ID contains significant bits of the destination prefix
                      padded with zeroes up to the next byte boundary).</t>
                      <t hangText="129    :">UTF-8 String (e.g. FQDN).</t>
                      <t hangText="130-255:">Reserved for future additions.</t>
                  </list></t>

              <t hangText="Domain Identifier: ">A variable length identifier
              of the given type.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="DHCP Data TLVs">
          <t>Auxiliary connectivity information is encoded as a stream of
          DHCP options. Such TLVs MUST only be present in an
          External Connection TLV or a Delegated Prefix TLV. When included in
          an External Connection TLV, they MUST contain DHCP options which are
          relevant to the whole External Connection. When included in a
          Delegated Prefix, they MUST contain DHCP options which are specific
          to the Delegated Prefix.</t>
          <t>The DHCPv6 Data TLV uses the following format:
            <figure>
              <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: DHCPV6-DATA (37)     |          Length: > 0          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      DHCPv6 option stream                     |
              </artwork>
            </figure>

            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="DHCPv6 option stream: ">DHCPv6 options encoded as
              specified in <xref target="RFC3315"/>.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The DHCPv4 Data TLV uses the following format:
            <figure>
              <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type: DHCPV4-DATA (38)    |          Length: > 0          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       DHCPv4 option stream                    |
              </artwork>
            </figure>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="DHCPv4 option stream: ">DHCPv4 options encoded as
              specified in <xref target="RFC2131"/>.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="pa" title="Prefix Assignment">
        <t>HNCP uses the Distributed Prefix Assignment Algorithm specified in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-prefix-assignment" /> in order to
        assign prefixes to HNCP internal links and uses the terminology
        defined there.</t>

    <section title="Prefix Assignment Algorithm Parameters">
    <t>All HNCP nodes running the prefix assignment algorithm MUST use
        the following parameters:

        <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Node IDs: ">HNCP node identifiers are used. The
                comparison operation is defined as bit-wise comparison.</t>

            <t hangText="Set of Delegated Prefixes: ">The set of prefixes
                encoded in Delegated Prefix TLVs which are not strictly included
                in prefixes encoded in other Delegated Prefix TLVs. Note that
                Delegated Prefix TLVs included in ignored External Connection
                TLVs are not considered. It is dynamically updated as Delegated
                Prefix TLVs are added or removed.</t>

            <t hangText="Set of Shared Links: ">The set of Common Links associated
                with internal, leaf, guest or ad-hoc interfaces. It is dynamically updated as
                HNCP interfaces are added, removed, or switch from one category to another.
                When multiple interfaces are detected as belonging to the same Common Link,
                prefix assignment is disabled on all of these interfaces except one.</t>

            <t hangText="Set of Private Links: ">This document defines
                Private Links representing DHCPv6-PD clients or as a mean to
                advertise prefixes included in the DHCPv6 Exclude Prefix option.
                Other implementation-specific Private Links may be defined whenever
                a prefix needs to be assigned for a purpose that does not require
                a consensus with other HNCP routers.</t>

            <t hangText="Set of Advertised Prefixes: ">The set of prefixes
                included in Assigned Prefix TLVs advertised by other HNCP
                routers (Prefixes advertised by the local node are not in this set).
                The associated Advertised Prefix Priority is the
                priority specified in the TLV. The associated Shared Link
                is determined as follows:

                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>If the Link Identifier is zero, the Advertised Prefix
                        is not assigned on a Shared Link.</t>

                    <t>If the other node's interface identified by the Link Identifier
                        is included in one of the Common Links used for prefix assignment, it is
                        considered as assigned on the given Common Link.
                    </t>
                    <t>Otherwise, the Advertised Prefix is not assigned on a Shared Link.</t>

                </list>

                Advertised Prefixes as well as their associated priorities
                and associated Shared Links MUST be updated as Assigned
                Prefix TLVs are added, updated or removed, and as Common Links
                are modified.
            </t>
            <t hangText="ADOPT_MAX_DELAY: ">The default value is 0
                seconds (i.e. prefix adoption MAY be done instantly).</t>

            <t hangText="BACKOFF_MAX_DELAY: ">The default value is
                4 seconds.</t>

            <t hangText="RANDOM_SET_SIZE: ">The default value is 64.</t>

            <t hangText="Flooding Delay: ">The default value is
                5 seconds.</t>

            <t hangText="Default Advertised Prefix Priority: ">When a
                new assignment is created or an assignment is adopted -
                as specified in the prefix assignment algorithm routine -
                the default Advertised Prefix Priority to be used is 2.</t>
        </list>
    </t>
</section>

        <section title="Assigned Prefix TLV">
          <t>Published Assigned Prefixes MUST be advertised using the Assigned
          Prefix TLV:</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type: ASSIGNED-PREFIX (35)   |          Length: >= 6         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Endpoint Identifier                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Rsv. | Prty. | Prefix Length |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+            Prefix             +
|                                                               |
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Endpoint Identifier: ">The endpoint identifier
              of the local interface that belongs to the Common Link the
              prefix is assigned to, or 0 if the Common Link is a Private
              Link (e.g., when the prefix is assigned for downstream prefix
              delegation).</t>


              <t hangText="Rsv.: ">Bits are reserved for future use. They
              MUST be set to zero when creating this TLV, and their value
              MUST be ignored when processing the TLV.</t>

              <t hangText="Prty: ">The Advertised Prefix Priority from 0 to 15.
                  <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="0-1  :">Low priorities.</t>
                      <t hangText="2    :">Default priority.</t>
                      <t hangText="3-7  :">High priorities.</t>
                      <t hangText="8-11 :">Administrative priorities. MUST NOT
                          be used unless configured otherwise.</t>
                      <t hangText="12-14:">Reserved for future use.</t>
                      <t hangText="15   :">Provider priorities. MAY only be used
                          by the router advertising the corresponding
                          delegated prefix and based on static or dynamic
                          configuration (e.g., for excluding a prefix based on
                          <xref target="RFC6603">DHCPv6-PD Prefix Exclude Option</xref>).
                      </t>
                  </list>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Prefix Length: ">The number of significant bits
              in the Prefix field.</t>

              <t hangText="Prefix: ">The significant bits of the prefix padded
              with zeroes up to the next byte boundary.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>



          <section title="Making New Assignments">
            <t>Whenever the Prefix Assignment Algorithm subroutine is run on a
            Common Link and whenever a new prefix may be assigned (case 1
            of the subroutine), the decision of whether the assignment of a new
            prefix is desired MUST follow these rules:

            <list style="hanging">
              <t>If the Delegated Prefix TLV contains a DHCPv4 or DHCPv6
              Data TLV, and the meaning of one of the DHCP options is not
              understood by the HNCP router, the creation of a new prefix
              is not desired.</t>

              <t>If the remaining preferred lifetime of the prefix is 0 and
              there is another delegated prefix of the same IP version used for
              prefix assignment with a non-null preferred lifetime, the
              creation of a new prefix is not desired.</t>

              <t>Otherwise, the creation of a new prefix is desired.</t>
            </list>
            </t>

            <t>If the considered delegated prefix is an IPv6 prefix, and
            whenever there is at least one available prefix of length 64, a
            prefix of length 64 MUST be selected unless configured
            otherwise by an administrator. In case no prefix of length 64
            would be available, a longer prefix MAY be selected.</t>

            <t>If the considered delegated prefix is an IPv4 prefix (<xref
            target="ula" /> details how IPv4 delegated prefixes are
            generated), a prefix of length 24 SHOULD be preferred.</t>

            <t>In any case, a router MUST support a mechanism suitable to
            distribute addresses from the considered prefix to clients on
            the link. Otherwise it MUST NOT create or adopt it, i.e. a
            router assigning an IPv4 prefix MUST support the L-capability
            and a router assigning an IPv6 prefix not suitable for
            Stateless Address Autoconfiguration MUST support the H-capability as
            defined in <xref target="version-tlv" />.
            </t>

          </section>

          <section title="Applying Assignments">
            <t>The prefix assignment algorithm indicates when a prefix is
            applied to the respective Common Link. When that happens
            each router connected to said link:

            <list>
              <t>MUST create an appropriate route for said prefix, indicating
              it is directly reachable on the respective link
              and advertise said route using the chosen routing protocol.</t>

              <t>MUST participate in the client configuration election as
              described in <xref target="client-config" />.</t>

              <t>MAY add an address from said prefix to the respective
              network interface as described in <xref target="node-addr" />,
              if it is to be used as source for locally originating traffic.
              </t>
            </list>

            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="DHCPv6-PD Excluded Prefix Support">
            <t>Whenever a <xref target="RFC6603">DHCPv6 Prefix Exclude option
            </xref> is received with a delegated prefix, the excluded prefix
            MUST be advertised as assigned to a Private Link with the maximum
            priority (i.e. 15).</t>

            <t>The same procedure MAY be applied in order to exclude
            prefixes obtained by other means of configuration.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Downstream Prefix Delegation Support" anchor="pd">
            <t>When an HNCP router receives a request for prefix delegation,
            it SHOULD assign one prefix per delegated prefix in the network.
            This set of assigned prefix is then delegated to the client,
            after it has been applied as described in the Prefix Assignment
            Algorithm. Each client MUST be considered as an independent
            Private Link and delegation MUST be based on the same set of
            Delegated Prefixes as the one used for Common Link prefix
            assignments.</t>

            <t>The assigned prefixes MUST NOT be given to clients before
            they are applied, and MUST be withdrawn whenever they are
            destroyed. As an exception to this rule, in order to shorten
            delays of processed requests, a router MAY prematurely
            give out a prefix which is advertised but not yet applied if it
            does so with a valid lifetime of not more than 30 seconds and
            ensures removal or correction of lifetimes as soon as possible.</t>
          </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Node Address Assignment" anchor="node-addr">
          <t>This section specifies how HNCP nodes reserve addresses for their
          own use. Nodes MAY, at any time, try to reserve a new address from any
          applied Assigned Prefix. SLAAC SHOULD be used whenever possible.
          The following method MUST be used otherwise.</t>

          <t>For any IPv6 prefix for which SLAAC cannot be used (resp. any IPv4 prefix)
          assigned to a Common Link, the first quarter of the addresses
          are reserved for routers HNCP based address assignments, whereas the last
          three quarters are left to the DHCPv6 (resp. DHCPv4) elected router
          (<xref target="version-tlv" /> specifies the DHCP server election process).
          For instance, if the prefix 192.0.2.0/24 is assigned and
          applied to a Common Link, addresses included in 192.0.2.0/26 are
          reserved for HNCP nodes and the remaining addresses are reserved
          for the elected DHCPv4 server.</t>

          <t>HNCP routers assign themselves addresses using the Node Address TLV:
            <figure>
              <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: NODE-ADDRESS (36)    |           Length: 20          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Endpoint Identifier                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                           IP Address                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
              </artwork>
            </figure>
            <list style="hanging">

              <t hangText="Endpoint Identifier: ">The endpoint identifier
              of the local interface that belongs to the Common Link the
              prefix is assigned to, or 0 if it is not assigned on an HNCP
              enabled link.</t>

              <t hangText="IP Address: ">The globally scoped IPv6 address, or the IPv4 address
              encoded as an <xref target="RFC4291">IPv4-mapped IPv6 address</xref>.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>The process of obtaining addresses is specified as follows:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>A router MUST NOT start advertising an address if it is
              already advertised by another router.</t>

              <t>An assigned address MUST be in the first quarter of an
              assigned prefix currently applied on a Common Link which includes
                  the interface specified by the endpoint identifier.</t>

              <t>An address MUST NOT be used unless it has been advertised for
              at least ADDRESS_APPLY_DELAY consecutive seconds, and is still
              currently being advertised. The default value for ADDRESS_APPLY_DELAY
              is 3 seconds.</t>

              <t>Whenever the same address is advertised by more than one node,
              all but the one advertised by the node with the highest node identifier
              MUST be removed.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ula" title="Local IPv4 and ULA Prefixes">
          <t>HNCP routers can create an ULA or private IPv4 prefix to enable
          connectivity between local devices. These prefixes are inserted in
          HNCP as if they were delegated prefixes. The following rules apply:

          <list>
            <t>An HNCP router SHOULD create a ULA prefix if there is no other
            non-deprecated IPv6 prefix in the network. It MAY also do so
            if there are other delegated IPv6 prefixes but none of which is
            generated by an HNCP router (i.e., none of which is specified in a
            Delegated Prefix TLV which also includes a Prefix Domain TLV)
            but MUST NOT do so otherwise. Whenever it detects
            another non-deprecated IPv6 prefix generated by an HNCP router with
            a greater HNCP identifier, it MUST cease to announce its own locally generated one.</t>

            <t>An HNCP router MUST create a <xref target="RFC1918">
            private IPv4 prefix</xref> whenever it wishes to provide IPv4 internet
            connectivity to the network and no other private IPv4 prefix with
            internet connectivity currently exists. It MAY also enable local IPv4
            connectivity by creating a private IPv4 prefix if no IPv4 prefix exists
            but MUST NOT do so otherwise.
            In case multiple IPv4 prefixes are announced all but one MUST be removed
            while those associated with a Prefix Domain TLV of type 0
            take precedence over those without and, in case of a tie, announcements by nodes
            with a greater node identifier take precedence over those with a
            lower one. The router publishing a prefix with internet connectivity
            MUST announce an IPv4 default route using the routing protocol and
            perform NAT on behalf of the network as long as it publishes the
            prefix, other routers in the network MAY choose not to.
            Internet Connectivity is indicated using a Prefix Domain TLV.</t>
          </list>

          </t>

          <t>Creation of such ULA and IPv4 prefixes MUST be delayed by a
          random timespan between 0 and 10 seconds in which the router MUST
          scan for other nodes trying to do the same.</t>

          <t>When a new ULA prefix is created, the prefix is selected based
          on the configuration, using the last non-deprecated ULA prefix,
          or generated based on <xref target="RFC4193"/>.</t>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Configuration of Hosts and non-HNCP Routers" anchor="client-config">
      <t>HNCP routers need to ensure that hosts and non-HNCP downstream
      routers on internal links are configured with addresses and routes.
      Since DHCP-clients can usually only bind to one server at a time, a per-link
      and per-service election takes place.</t>

      <t>HNCP routers may have different capabilities for configuring
      downstream devices and providing naming services. Each router MUST
      therefore indicate its capabilities as specified in <xref
      target="version-tlv" /> in order to participate as a candidate in the
      election.</t>

      <section title="DHCPv6 for Addressing or Configuration">
        <t>In general Stateless Address Autoconfiguration is used for client
        configuration for its low overhead and fast renumbering capabilities,
        however stateful DHCPv6 can be used in addition by administrative choice,
        to e.g. collect hostnames and use them to provide naming services
        or whenever stateless configuration is not applicable.</t>

        <t>The designated stateful DHCPv6 server for a <xref
        target="links">Common Link</xref> is elected
        based on the capabilities described in <xref target="version-tlv"
        />.  The winner is the router (connected to the Common Link) advertising the greatest
        H-capability. In case of a tie, Capability Values and node
        identifiers are considered (greatest value is elected). The
        elected router MUST serve stateful DHCPv6 and MUST provide naming services for
        acquired hostnames as outlined in <xref target="naming-sd" />.
        Stateful addresses SHOULD be assigned in a way not hindering
        fast renumbering even if the DHCPv6 server or client do not support
        the DHCPv6 reconfigure mechanism. In case no router was
        elected, stateful DHCPv6 is not provided and each router assigning
        IPv6-prefixes on said link MUST provide stateless DHCPv6 service.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Sending Router Advertisements">
          <t>All HNCP routers MUST send Router Advertisements periodically via multicast and via unicast in
              response to Router Solicitations.

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>The "Managed address configuration" flag MUST be set whenever
          a router connected to the link is advertising a non-null
          H-capability and MUST NOT be set otherwise. The "Other configuration"
          flag MUST always be set.</t>

          <t>The default Router Lifetime MUST be set to an appropriate non-null value
          whenever an IPv6 default route is known in the HNCP network and
          MUST be set to zero otherwise.</t>

          <t>A Prefix Information Option MUST be added for each assigned and applied IPv6
          prefix on the given link. The autonomous address-configuration flag
          MUST be set whenever the prefix is suitable for stateless
          configuration. The preferred and valid lifetimes MUST be
          smaller than the preferred and valid lifetimes of the
          delegated prefix the prefix is from. When a prefix is removed,
          it MUST be deprecated as specified in <xref target="RFC7084"/>.</t>

          <t>A <xref target="RFC4191">Route Information Option</xref> MUST be
          added for each delegated IPv6 prefix known in the HNCP network.
          Additional ones SHOULD be added for each non-default IPv6 route
          with an external destination prefix advertised by the routing protocol.</t>

          <t>A Recursive DNS Server Option and a DNS Search List Option MUST
          be included with appropriate contents.</t>

          <t>To allow for optimized routing decisions for clients on the local
          link routers SHOULD adjust their <xref target="RFC4191">Default
          Router Preference and Route Preferences</xref> so that the priority
          is set to low if the next hop of the default or more specific route
          is on the same interface as the Route Advertisement being sent on.
          Similarly the router MAY use the high priority if it is certain it
          has the best metric of all routers on the link for all routes known
          in the network with the respective destination.</t>
        </list>

        Every router sending Router Advertisements MUST immediately send an
        updated Router Advertisement via multicast as soon as it notices a
        condition resulting in a change of any advertised information.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCPv6 for Prefix Delegation">

        <t>The designated DHCPv6 server for prefix-delegation on a Common Link is
        elected based on the capabilities described in <xref
        target="version-tlv" />.

        The winner is the router (connected to the Common Link) advertising
        the greatest P-capability. In case of a tie, Capability Values are
        compared, and router with the greatest value is elected. In case of
        another tie, the router with the highest node identifier is elected
        among the routers with tied Capability Values.

        The elected router MUST provide <xref
        target="RFC3633">prefix-delegation services</xref> on the given
        link and follow the rules in <xref target="pd" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCPv4 for Addressing and Configuration">
        <t>The designated DHCPv4 server on a <xref
        target="links">Common Link</xref> is elected based on the
        capabilities described in <xref target="version-tlv" />.

        The winner is the router (connected to the Common Link) advertising
        the greatest L-capability. In case of a tie, Capability Values are
        compared, and router with the greatest value is elected. In case of
        another tie, the router with the highest node identifier is elected
        among the routers with tied Capability Values.

        The elected router MUST provide
        DHCPv4 services on the given link.</t>

        <t>The DHCPv4 serving router MUST announce itself as
        <xref target="RFC2132">router</xref> to clients if and only if there
        is an IPv4 default route known in the network. In addition, the router
        SHOULD announce a
        <xref target="RFC3442">Classless Static Route Option</xref>
        for each non-default IPv4 route advertised in the routing protocol
        with an external destination.</t>

        <t>DHCPv4 lease times SHOULD be short (i.e. not longer than 5 minutes)
        in order to provide reasonable response times to changes.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multicast DNS Proxy">
        <t>The designated <xref target="RFC6762">MDNS</xref> proxy on a
        Common Link is elected based on the capabilities described in <xref
        target="version-tlv" />.

        The winner is the router (connected to the Common Link) advertising
        the greatest M-capability. In case of a tie, Capability Values are
        compared, and router with the greatest value is elected. In case of
        another tie, the router with the highest node identifier is elected
        among the routers with tied Capability Values.

        The elected router MUST provide an MDNS-proxy on the given link and
        announce it as described in <xref target="naming-sd" />.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Naming and Service Discovery" anchor="naming-sd">

      <t>Network-wide naming and service discovery can greatly improve the
      user-friendliness of an IPv6 network. The following mechanism provides
      means to setup and delegate naming and service discovery across
      multiple HNCP routers.</t>

      <t>Each HNCP router SHOULD provide and announce an auto-generated or
      user-configured name for each internal <xref target="links">Common
      Link</xref> for which it is the designated DHCPv4, stateful
      DHCPv6 server or MDNS proxy and for
      which it provides DNS services on behalf of devices on said link.
      In addition it MAY provide reverse lookup services.</t>
      <t>The following TLVs are defined and MUST be supported by all nodes
      implementing naming and service discovery:</t>

      <section anchor="delegated-zone-tlv" title="DNS Delegated Zone TLV">

        <t>This TLV is used to announce a forward or reverse DNS zone
        delegation in the HNCP network. Its meaning is roughly equivalent
        to specifying an NS and A/AAAA record for said zone. There MUST NOT
        be more than one delegation for the same zone in the whole DNCP
        network. In case of a conflict the announcement of the node with
        the highest node identifier takes precedence and all other nodes
        MUST cease to announce the conflicting TLV.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Type: DNS-DELEGATED-ZONE (39) |        Length: >= 17          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                           IP Address                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Reserved |L|B|S|                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  Zone (DNS label sequence - variable length)  |
|                                                               |
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="IP Address :"> The IPv6 address of the authoritative
            DNS server for the zone; IPv4 addresses are represented as
            <xref target="RFC4291">IPv4-mapped addresses</xref>.  The
            special value of :: (all-zero) means the delegation is
            available in the global DNS-hierarchy.</t>

            <t hangText="Reserved :">Those bits MUST be set to zero when creating the TLV
                and ignored when parsing it unless defined in a later specification.</t>

            <t hangText="L-bit :"> <xref target="RFC6763">DNS-SD</xref> Legacy-Browse,
            indicates that this delegated zone should be included in the
            network's DNS-SD legacy browse list of domains at lb._dns-
            sd._udp.(DOMAIN-NAME).  Local forward zones SHOULD have this
            bit set, reverse zones SHOULD NOT.</t>

            <t hangText="B-bit :"> (<xref target="RFC6763">DNS-SD</xref> Browse)
            indicates that this delegated zone should be included in the
            network's DNS-SD browse list of domains at b._dns-sd._udp.
            (DOMAIN-NAME).  Local forward zones SHOULD have this bit set,
            reverse zones SHOULD NOT.</t>

            <t hangText="S-bit :"> (fully-qualified <xref target="RFC6763">DNS-SD</xref>
             domain) indicates that this delegated zone consists of a
            fully-qualified DNS-SD domain, which should be used as base for
            DNS-SD domain enumeration, i.e. _dns-sd._udp.(Zone) exists.
            Forward zones MAY have this bit set, reverse zones MUST NOT.
            This can be used to provision DNS search path to hosts for
            non-local services (such as those provided by an ISP, or other
            manually configured service providers). Zones with this flag
            SHOULD be added to the search domains advertised to clients.</t>

            <t hangText="Zone :">The label sequence of the zone, encoded as
            the domain names are encoded DNS messages as specified in <xref
            target="RFC1035"/>. The last label in the zone MUST be
            empty.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>


      <section anchor="domain-name-tlv" title="Domain Name TLV">

        <t>This TLV is used to indicate the base domain name for the
        network.  It is the zone used as a base for all non fully-qualified
        delegated zones and node names.  In case of conflicts the announced
        domain of the node with the greatest node identifier takes precedence.
        By default, i.e., if no node advertises such a TLV., ".home" is used.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: DOMAIN-NAME (40)     |         Length: > 0           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        Domain (DNS label sequence - variable length)          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Domain: ">The label sequence encoded according to <xref
            target="RFC1035"/>.  Compression MUST NOT be used. The zone
            MUST end with an empty label.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="router-name-tlv" title="Node Name TLV">

        <t>This TLV is used to assign the name of a node in the network
        to a certain IP address. In case of conflicts the announcement of
        the node with the greatest node identifier for a name takes precedence
        and all other nodes MUST cease to announce the conflicting TLV.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type: NODE-NAME (41)      |         Length: > 16          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                           IP Address                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Name (not null-terminated - variable length)          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="IP Address: ">The IP address associated with the name. IPv4
            addresses are encoded using IPv4-mapped IPv6 addresses.</t>

            <t hangText="Name: ">The name of the node as a DNS label. The
            length of the label is the Length value of the TLV minus
            16. </t>

        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Securing Third-Party Protocols">
      <t>Pre-shared keys (PSKs) are often required to secure IGPs and other
      protocols which lack support for asymmetric security. The following
      mechanism manages PSKs using HNCP to enable bootstrapping of such
      third-party protocols and SHOULD therefore be used if such a need
      arises. The following rules define how such a PSK is managed and used:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>If no Managed-PSK-TLV is currently being announced, an HNCP
        router MUST create one after a random delay of 0 to 10 seconds
        with a 32 bytes long random key and add it to its node data.</t>
        <t>In case multiple routers announce such a TLV at the same time,
        all but the one with the greatest node identifier stop advertising it and
        adopt the remaining one.</t>
        <t>The router currently advertising the Managed-PSK-TLV must
        generate and advertise a new random one whenever an unreachable node
        is purged as described in DNCP.</t>
        <!-- [PP] Shouldn't we add some grace period to that. Changing the key
         is an heavy operation which we probably don't want to do when there
         is a flappy link. -->
      </list>
      </t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: Managed-PSK (42)     |          Length: 32           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                           Random PSK                          |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>PSKs for individual protocols are derived from the random PSK
      through the use of <xref target="RFC6234">HMAC-SHA256</xref> with a
      pre-defined per-protocol HMAC-key in ASCII-format. The following
      HMAC-keys are currently defined to derive PSKs for the respective
      protocols:

      <list>
        <t>"ROUTING": to be used for IGPs</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="version-tlv" title="HNCP Versioning and Capabilities">

      <t>Multiple versions of HNCP based on compatible
      DNCP profiles may be
      present in the same network when transitioning between HNCP versions
      and HNCP routers may have different capabilities to support clients.
      The following mechanism describes a way to announce the currently active
      version and User-agent of a node. Each node MUST include an
      HNCP-Version-TLV in its Node Data and MUST ignore (except for DNCP
      synchronization purposes) any TLVs with a type greater than 32 published
      by nodes not also publishing an HNCP-Version TLV or publishing such a TLV with a
      different Version number.</t>

      <t>Capabilities are indicated by setting M, P, H and L fields in the TLV. The
      "capability value" is a metric indicated by interpreting the bits as an
      integer, i.e. (M &lt;&lt; 12 | P &lt;&lt; 8 | H &lt;&lt; 4 | L).</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Type: HNCP-VERSION (32)    |         Length: >= 5          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Version    |   Reserved    |   M   |   P   |   H   |   L   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                          User-agent                           |
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
          <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Version:">Indicates which version of HNCP is
                  currently in use by this particular node. It MUST be set to 1.
                  Nodes with different versions are considered incompatible.
              </t>

              <t hangText="Reserved:">Bits are reserved for future use. They
              MUST be set to zero when creating this TLV, and their value
              MUST be ignored when processing the TLV.
              </t>
              <t hangText="M-capability:">Priority value used for electing the
                  on-link <xref target="RFC6762">MDNS</xref> proxy. It MUST be
                  set to some value between 1 and 7 included (4 is the default)
                  if the router is capable of proxying MDNS and 0 otherwise.
                  The values 8-15 are reserved for future use.</t>
              <t hangText="P-capability:">Priority value used for electing the
                  on-link DHCPv6-PD server. It MUST be set to some value between
                  1 and 7 included (4 is the default) if the router is capable of
                  <xref target="pd">providing prefixes through DHCPv6-PD</xref>
                  and 0 otherwise.
                  The values 8-15 are reserved for future use.</t>
              <t hangText="H-capability:">Priority value used for electing the
                  on-link DHCPv6 server offering non-temporary addresses.  It
                  MUST be set to some value between 1 and 7 included
                  (4 is the default) if the router is capable of providing such
                  addresses and 0 otherwise.
                  The values 8-15 are reserved for future use.</t>
              <t hangText="L-capability:">Priority value used for electing the
                  on-link DHCPv4 server. It MUST be set to some value between
                  1 and 7 included (4 is the default) if the router is
                  capable of running a legacy DHCPv4 server offering
                  IPv4 addresses to clients and 0 otherwise.
                  The values 8-15 are reserved for future use.</t>
              <t hangText="User-Agent:">
                  The user-agent is a human-readable UTF-8 string
                  that describes the name and version of the current HNCP
                  implementation.
              </t>
          </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Requirements for HNCP Routers">
      <t>Each router implementing HNCP is subject to the following
      requirements:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>It MUST implement HNCP-Versioning, Border Discovery, Prefix
        Assignment and Configuration of hosts and non-HNCP routers
        as defined in this document.</t>
        <t>It MUST implement and run the method for securing third-party
        protocols whenever it uses the security mechanism of HNCP.</t>
        <t>It SHOULD implement support for the Service Discovery and Naming
        TLVs as defined in this document.</t>
        <t>It MUST implement and run a routing protocol appropriate for the
        given link type on all of the interfaces it sends and receives HNCP
        traffic on. The protocol MUST support source-specific routes and
        MUST correctly propagate those also for the external destinations
        that may have only implicit source-specific information, such as
        a combination of a DHCPv6 PD-derived prefix and a non-source-specific
        default route.</t>
        <t>It MUST use adequate security mechanisms for the routing
        protocol on any interface where it also uses the security
        mechanisms of HNCP. If the security mechanism is based on a PSK it
        MUST use a PSK derived from the Managed-PSK to secure the IGP.</t>
        <t>It MAY be able to provide connectivity to IPv4-devices using
        DHCPv4.</t>
        <t>It SHOULD be able to delegate prefixes to legacy IPv6 routers
        using DHCPv6-PD.</t>
        <t>In addition, normative language of <xref target="RFC7084">Basic
        Requirements for IPv6 Customer Edge Routers</xref> applies with the
        following adjustments:
        <list>
            <t>The section "WAN-Side Configuration" applies to HNCP interfaces
        	classified as external.</t>
        	<t>If the CE sends a size-hint as indicated in WPD-2, the hint
        	MUST NOT be determined by the number of LAN-interfaces of the CE,
        	but SHOULD instead be large enough to at least accommodate prefix
        	assignments announced for existing delegated or ULA-prefixes, if
        	such prefixes exist and unless explicitly configured otherwise.</t>
        	<t>The dropping of packets with a destination address belonging to
        	a delegated prefix mandated in WPD-5 MUST NOT be applied to
        	destinations that are part of any prefix announced using an
        	ASSIGNED-PREFIX TLV by any HNCP router in the network.</t>
        	<t>The section "LAN-Side Configuration" applies to HNCP interfaces
        	classified as internal.</t>
        	<t>The requirement to assign a separate /64 to each LAN interface,
        	L-2, is replaced by the participation in the <xref target="pa">
        	prefix assignment mechanism</xref> for each such interface.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>HNCP enables self-configuring networks, requiring
      as little user intervention as possible. However this
      zero-configuration goal usually conflicts with security goals and
      introduces a number of threats.</t>

      <t>General security issues for existing home networks are discussed
      in <xref target="RFC7368" />. The protocols used to set up addresses
      and routes in such networks to this day rarely have security enabled
      within the configuration protocol itself. However these issues are out
      of scope for the security of HNCP itself.</t>

      <t>HNCP is a DNCP-based
      state synchronization mechanism carrying information with varying
      threat potential. For this consideration the payloads defined in DNCP
      and this document are reviewed:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Network topology information such as HNCP nodes and their
        common links.</t>

        <t>Address assignment information such as delegated and assigned
        prefixes for individual links.</t>

        <t>Naming and service discovery information such as auto-generated
        or customized names for individual links and routers.</t>

      </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Border Determination">

        <t>As described in <xref target="bd" />, an HNCP router determines
        the internal or external state on a per-link basis. A firewall
        perimeter is set up for the external links, and for internal links,
        HNCP and IGP traffic is allowed.</t>

        <t>Threats concerning automatic border discovery cannot be
        mitigated by encrypting or authenticating HNCP traffic itself since
        external routers do not participate in the protocol and often
        cannot be authenticated by other means. These threats include
        propagation of forged uplinks in the homenet in order to
        e.g. redirect traffic destined to external locations and forged
        internal status by external routers to e.g. circumvent the
        perimeter firewall.</t>

        <t>It is therefore imperative to either secure individual links on
        the physical or link-layer or preconfigure the adjacent interfaces
        of HNCP routers to an adequate fixed-category in order to secure
        the homenet border.  Depending on the security of the external link
        eavesdropping, man-in-the-middle and similar attacks on external
        traffic can still happen between a homenet border router and the
        ISP, however these cannot be mitigated from inside the homenet. For
        example, DHCPv4 has defined <xref target="RFC3118" /> to authenticate
        DHCPv4 messages, but this is very rarely implemented in large or
        small networks.  Further, while PPP can provide secure
        authentication of both sides of a point to point link, it is most
        often deployed with one-way authentication of the subscriber to the
        ISP, not the ISP to the subscriber.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Security of Unicast Traffic">

        <t>Once the homenet border has been established there are several
        ways to secure HNCP against internal threats like manipulation or
        eavesdropping by compromised devices on a link which is enabled for
        HNCP traffic. If left unsecured, attackers may perform arbitrary
        eavesdropping, spoofing or denial of service attacks on HNCP services
        such as address assignment or service discovery.</t>


        <t>Detailed interface categories like "leaf" or "guest" can be used
        to integrate not fully trusted devices to various degrees into the
        homenet by not exposing them to HNCP and IGP traffic or by using
        firewall rules to prevent them from reaching homenet-internal
        resources. </t>

        <t>On links where this is not practical and lower layers do not
        provide adequate protection from attackers, DNCP secure mode MUST be
        used to secure traffic.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Other Protocols in the Home">

        <t>IGPs and other protocols are usually run alongside HNCP therefore
        the individual security aspects of the respective protocols must be
        considered.  It can however be summarized that many protocols to be
        run in the home (like IGPs) provide - to a certain extent - similar
        security mechanisms.  Most of these protocols do not support
        encryption and only support authentication based on pre-shared keys
        natively.  This influences the effectiveness of any encryption-based
        security mechanism deployed by HNCP as homenet routing information is
        thus usually not encrypted.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>IANA is requested to maintain a registry for HNCP TLV-Types.
      This registry inherits TLV-Types and allocation policy defined in
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-dncp">DNCP</xref>, but is independent
      with regard to all TLV-Types not specified or reserved by DNCP. Particularly,
      other DNCP profile may have there own registries, using same TLV numbers.</t>

      <t>The following TLV-Types are defined in this document:

      <list>
        <t>32: HNCP-Version</t>
        <t>33: External-Connection</t>
        <t>34: Delegated-Prefix</t>
        <t>35: Assigned-Prefix</t>
        <t>36: Node-Address</t>
        <t>37: DHCPv4-Data</t>
        <t>38: DHCPv6-Data</t>
        <t>39: DNS-Delegated-Zone</t>
        <t>40: Domain-Name</t>
        <t>41: Node-Name</t>
        <t>42: Managed-PSK</t>
      </list>

      </t>

      <t>HNCP requires allocation of UDP port numbers
      HNCP-UDP-PORT and HNCP-DTLS-PORT, as well as an IPv6 link-local
      multicast address All-Homenet-Routers.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-homenet-dncp-06"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6603.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4191.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-homenet-prefix-assignment-07"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7084.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3004.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3118.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2131.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1918.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4291.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7368.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6234.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1321.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6762.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6763.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6241.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2132.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3442.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4193.xml"?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changelog [RFC Editor: please remove]">

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-07: Using version 1 instead of version 0,
      as existing implementations already use it.</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-06: Various edits based on feedback,
      hopefully without functional delta.</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-05: Renamed "Adjacent Link" to "Common Link".
      Changed single IPv4 uplink election from MUST to MAY. Added explicit
      indication to distinguish (IPv4)-PDs for local connectivity and ones
      with uplink connectivity allowing e.g. better local-only
      IPv4-connectivity.</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-04: Change the responsibility for sending
      RAs to the router assigning the prefix.</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-03: Split to DNCP (generic protocol) and
      HNCP (homenet profile).</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-02: Removed any built-in security. Relying
      on IPsec. Reorganized interface categories, added requirements languages,
      made manual border configuration a MUST-support. Redesigned routing
      protocol election to consider non-router devices.</t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-01: Added (MAY) guest, ad-hoc, hybrid
      categories for interfaces. Removed old hnetv2 reference, and now
      pointing just to OpenWrt + github. Fixed synchronization algorithm to
      spread also same update number, but different data hash case. Made
      purge step require bidirectional connectivity between nodes when
      traversing the graph. Edited few other things to be hopefully
      slightly clearer without changing their meaning. </t>

      <t>draft-ietf-homenet-hncp-00: Added version TLV to allow for TLV content
      changes pre-RFC without changing IDs. Added link id to assigned
      address TLV. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Draft source [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>This draft is available at <eref
      target="https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/">https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/</eref>
      in source format. Issues and pull requests are welcome.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>A GPLv2-licensed implementation of HNCP is currently under
      development at <eref target="https://github.com/sbyx/hnetd/">
      https://github.com/sbyx/hnetd/</eref> and binaries are available in
      the <eref target="http://www.openwrt.org">OpenWrt</eref> package
      repositories.  See <eref
      target="http://www.homewrt.org/doku.php?id=run-conf" /> for more
      information.  Feedback and contributions are welcome.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>Thanks to Ole Troan, Mark Baugher, Mark Townsley
      and Juliusz Chroboczek for their contributions to the draft.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Eric Kline for the original border discovery work.</t>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
