<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!--
Created:       Fri Oct  2 12:47:06 2015 mstenber

-->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>

<?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<rfc
    ipr='trust200902'
    docName='draft-stenberg-mif-mpvd-dns-00'
    category='std'
    >
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPVD using DNS">
      Multiple Provisioning Domains using Domain Name System
    </title>
    <author initials="M" surname="Stenberg" fullname="Markus Stenberg">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Helsinki</city>
          <code>00930</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>markus.stenberg@iki.fi</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Barth" fullname="Steven Barth">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Halle</city>
          <code>06114</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cyrus@openwrt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2015" />

    <area>TBD</area>
    <workgroup>MIF Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>PVD</keyword>
    <keyword>DNS</keyword>
    <abstract>

      <t>This document describes a mechanism to transmit and secure
      provisioning domain information for IPv6 and IPv4 addresses by using
      reverse DNS resolution. In addition it specifies backwards-compatible
      extensions to IPv6 host configuration to support special-purpose
      global IPv6 prefixes which can only be used to access certain
      isolated services.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>Given multiple address prefixes and/or multiple interfaces, the
      hosts require more information to make educated choices about the
      interfaces and addresses to use. <xref target='RFC7556' /> describes
      the provision domains (PVDs) that provide the additional information
      the hosts need. </t>

      <t>This document describes where and how the provision domain
      information is encoded in the Domain Name System (DNS).
      <!-- TBD - keep or not?

      Two
      alternative authentication schemes are also provided to authenticate
      the DNS records, although unauthenticated records may be also useful
      in many cases.-->

      A backwards compatible way of adding IPv6 prefixes without generic
      internet connectivity is also provided so that the hosts that are not
      aware of the provisioning domain prefixes do not inadvertly use those
      for general network access. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">


      <texttable suppress-title="true" style="none" align="left">
	<ttcol width="25%" /><ttcol width="75%" />

	<c>PVD</c>

	<c>a provisioning domain, usually with a set of provisioning domain
	information; for more information, see <xref target="RFC7556"
	/>.</c>

	<c>special-purpose IPv6 prefix</c>
	<c>a global IPv6 source prefix that cannot be used to reach the
	public IPv6 internet but instead only allows access to certain
	special services (e.g., VoIP, IPTV).</c>

        <c /><c />

      </texttable>


      <section anchor="kwd" title='Requirements Language'>

        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
          be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'>RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Overview">

      <t>TBD</t>

    </section>

    <section title="PVD discovery using DNS">


      <t>The data for a single PVD within DNS is encoded as one TXT record,
      encoded similarly to the TXT records specified in <xref
      target="RFC6763">RFC6763 Section 6</xref>.

      This document specifies particular reserved keys and an extension
      mechanism in <xref target="keys" />.</t>

      <t>To find the per-PVD TXT records that apply to an address, given an
      address and its netmask, initially PTR records are queried for at
      _pvd.&lt;domain&gt;. The &lt;domain&gt; is derived from the address
      and its netmask, by generating it as specified in the <xref
      target="RFC6763">RFC6763 Section 11</xref>. As prefixes can be
      sub-delegated arbitrarily, PTR records should be provided for any
      subprefixes contained within a particular prefix. Then the FQDNs PTR
      records point at are queried to find the TXT records for the PVDs
      that apply to the particular address.</t>

      <!-- TBD: Note that caching MUST be implemented correctly by hosts,
           incl. negative entries -->

      <t>For example, given 2001:db8:8765:4321::/64 prefix, a node with an
      address of 2001:db8:8765:4321:1234:5678:abcd:beef queries for
      _pvd.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa
      for PTR(s) to PVD TXT records. However, if the address is
      subdelegated from 2001:db8:8765:4321:1234::/80, the request would be
      for
      _pvd.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.4.3.2.1.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa.

      Continuing the example, the retrieved PTR record points at FQDN
      _pvd.example.com. Therefore next query is sent for TXT records there,
      and when received, the node has up-to-date information about PVDs
      applicable to that particular address.</t>

      <t>A node MUST support multiple PTR records at the initial
      _pvd.&lt;domain&gt; as well as multiple TXT records where the PTR
      records point to. This facilitates handling of multiple PVDs with
      minimal amount of state in the network. A node MUST honor both the
      time-to-live of the received records, and negative replies that
      conform to <xref target="RFC2308" />.</t>


    <section anchor="keys" title="PVD TXT Record Keys">

      <t>While the format of the PVD TXT itself is reused from <xref
      target="RFC6763">RFC6763 Section 6</xref>, the format of the keys are
      defined here.</t>

      <section title="Reachable Services" anchor="keys-services">

    	<t>The following set of keys can be used to specify the set
    	of services for which the respective PVD should be used. If present
    	they MUST be honored by the client, i.e., if the PVD is marked as
    	not usable for internet access it MUST NOT be used for internet
    	access, if the usability is limited to a certain set of domain or
    	address prefixes, then a different PVD MUST be used for other
    	destinations.</t>

    	<texttable>
    	  <ttcol>Type</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol width="20%">Example</ttcol>
    	  <c>s</c>
    	  <c>Internet inaccessible</c>
    	  <c>(none)</c>
    	  <c>s</c>
    	  <c>z</c>
    	  <c>DNS zones accessible</c>
    	  <c>comma-separated list of DNS zone</c>
    	  <c>z=foo.com,sub.bar.com</c>
    	  <c>6</c>
    	  <c>IPv6-prefixes accessible</c>
    	  <c>comma-separated list of IPv6 prefixes</c>
    	  <c>6=2001:db8:a::/48,2001:db8:b:c::/64</c>
    	  <c>4</c>
    	  <c>IPv4-prefixes accessible</c>
    	  <c>comma-separated list of IPv4 prefixes in CIDR</c>
    	  <c>4=1.2.3.0/24,2.3.0.0/16</c>
    	</texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Configuration" anchor="keys-dns">

    	<t>The following set of keys can be used to specify the DNS
    	configuration for the respective PVD. If present, they MUST be
    	honored and used by the client whenever it wishes to access the
    	a resource of the PVD.</t>

    	<texttable>
    	  <ttcol>Type</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol width="20%">Example</ttcol>
    	  <c>r</c>
    	  <c>Recursive DNS server</c>
    	  <c>comma-separated list of IPv6 and IPv4 addresses</c>
    	  <c>r=2001:db8::1,192.0.2.2</c>
    	  <c>d</c>
    	  <c>DNS search domains</c>
    	  <c>comma-separated list of search domains</c>
    	  <c>d=foo.com,sub.bar.com</c>
    	</texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Connectivity Characteristics" anchor="keys-conn">

    	<t>The following set of keys can be used to signal certain
    	characteristics of the connection towards the PVD.</t>

    	<texttable>
    	  <ttcol>Type</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol width="20%">Value</ttcol>
    	  <ttcol width="20%">Example</ttcol>
    	  <c>bw</c>
    	  <c>Maximum achievable bandwidth</c>
    	  <c>1 symmetrical or 2 comma-separated ingress,
          egress values in kilobits per second</c>

    	  <c>bw=5000 or bw=1000,100</c>
    	  <c>lt</c>
    	  <c>Minimum achievable latency</c>
	  <c>1 symmetrical or 2 comma-separated ingress, egress values in
          milliseconds</c>

    	  <c>lt=20 ot lt=20,100</c>
    	  <c>rl</c>
    	  <c>Maximum achievable reliability</c>
	  <c>1 symmetrical or 2 comma-separated ingress, egress values in
          1/1000</c>
    	  <c>rl=1000 or rl=900,800</c>

    	  <c>tm</c>
    	  <c>Traffic metered (cut-off / limited over threshold)</c>
    	  <c>(none) or traffic threshold in kilobytes</c>
    	  <c>tm or tm=1000000</c>

    	  <c>cp</c>
    	  <c>Captive portal</c>
    	  <c>(none)</c>
    	  <c>cp</c>

    	  <c>nat</c>
    	  <c>IPv4 NAT in place</c>
    	  <c>(none)</c>
    	  <c>nat</c>
    	</texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Private Extensions" anchor="keys-private">
    	<t>keys starting with "x-" are reserved for private use and
    	can be utilized to provide vendor-, user- or enterprise-specific
    	information. It is RECOMMENDED to use one of the patterns
    	"x-FQDN-KEY[=VALUE]" or "x-PEN-KEY[=VALUE]" where FQDN is a fully
    	qualified domain name or PEN is a <xref target="PEN">private
    	enterprise number</xref> under control of the author of the
    	extension to avoid collisions.</t>
      </section>

    </section>
  </section>
    <section anchor="sp" title="Special-purpose IPv6 prefixes">
      <t>A service provider might wish to assign certain global unicast
      address prefixes which can be used to reach a limited set of services
      only. In the presence of legacy hosts it must be ensured however
      that these prefixes are not mistakenly used as source addresses for
      other destinations. This section therefore defines optional extensions
      to <xref target="RFC4861">NDP</xref>, <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6
      </xref> and <xref target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref> to indicate this
      state.</t>

      <section anchor="sp-slaac"
	       title="Extensions to Stateless Address Autoconfiguration">
	<t><xref target="RFC4861">NDP</xref> defines the Prefix
	Information option to announce prefixes for stateless address
	configuration. The "A-bit" is set, whenever hosts may autonomously
	derive addresses from a given prefix. For special-purpose prefixes
	this document defines the first bit of the Reserved1-field as the
	"S-Bit".</t>

	<figure>
          <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     | Prefix Length |L|A|S|Reserved1|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              ...                              |
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The following additional requirements apply to hosts intending
	to support global special-purpose IPv6 prefixes:
	<list>
	  <t>Upon reception of a Prefix Information Option with the
	  S-Bit set, it should behave as if the A-Bit was set, however
	  (unless the A-Bit was actually set by the sending router)
	  it MUST delay using any addresses derived from the prefix
	  until it has queried, retrieved and honored (see TODO)
	  at least all mandatory provisioning domain information related
	  to the given prefix.</t>

	  <t>A host SHOULD NOT interpret the S-Bit being clear as an
	  indicator that no provisioning domain information is available
	  for a given prefix.</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
	  The following additional requirements apply to routers:
	  <list>
	    <t>A router MUST NOT set the A-Bit for global unicast
	    address prefixes which cannot be used to reach the public
	    IPv6 internet.</t>

	    <t>A router SHOULD use the S-Bit to indicate that PVD-aware
	    hosts can statelessly assign themselves addresses from a given
	    prefix. It MAY use the S-Bit in addition to the A-Bit to
	    indicate that a prefix usable to reach the public IPv6
	    internet has additional (optional) provisioning domain
	    information.</t>

	    <t>A router announcing one or more Prefix Information options
	    with the S-Bit set MUST also announce one or more recursive
	    DNS servers using a <xref target="RFC6106">Recursive DNS Server
	    Option</xref>. If none of the Prefix Information Options it
	    announces have the A-Bit set then at least one of these
	    recursive DNS servers MUST be reachable using a link-local
	    address.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sp-dhcpv6" title="Extensions to DHCPv6">
	<t>Using <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref> and <xref
	target="RFC3633">DHCPv6-PD</xref> servers can actively decide which
	addresses or prefixes are assigned to clients and requesting routers,
	however a mechanism is needed to distinguish PVD-aware devices and
	in the same sense PVD-aware devices need to be able to detect which
	prefixes and addresses are special-purpose. Therefore, a zero-length
	DHCPv6 option OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE is defined to be added as a
	suboption to OPTION_IAADDR and OPTION_IAPREFIX options.</t>

	<figure>
          <artwork>
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE (TBD)  |               0               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The following additional requirements apply to clients and
	requesting routers intending to support global special-purpose IPv6
	prefixes via DHCPv6:
	<list>
	  <t>A client or requesting router MUST include the option code
	  OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE in an option OPTION_ORO in its SOLICIT and
	  REQUEST messages, whenever it wishes to accept special-purpose
	  prefixes in its identity associations.</t>

	  <t>Upon reception of an OPTION_IAADDR or OPTION_IAPREFIX option
	  having an embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option it MUST delay
	  using any addresses derived from the prefix as source address for
	  its own communication until it has queried, retrieved and
	  honored (see TODO) at least all mandatory provisioning domain
	  information related to the given prefix or address. If it is a
	  requesting router, it MAY however subdelegate prefixes or assign
	  addresses from special-purpose prefixes to clients without doing
	  so as long as the requirements in the following paragraph are
	  honored.</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>The following additional requirements apply to routers assigning
	addresses from or delegating (parts of) special-purpose prefixes
	using DHCPv6:
	<list>
	  <t>A router MUST include a zero-length suboption of type
	  OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE in every OPTION_IAADDR and OPTION_IAPREFIX
	  option it assigns or delegates containing a global unicast address
	  or prefix which cannot be used to reach the public IPv6 internet.
	  It MUST NOT assign or delegate such an address or prefix to a
	  client or requesting router not including the option code of
	  OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE inside an OPTION_ORO option.</t>

	  <t>A router announcing one or more addresses or prefixes
	  with an embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option MUST also announce
	  one or more recursive DNS servers using a <xref target="RFC3646">
	  OPTION_DNS_SERVERS option</xref>. If all of the addresses in a
	  DHCPv6 reply carry the embedded OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE option
	  then at least one of the announced recursive DNS servers MUST
	  be reachable using a link-local address.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>Security properties of NDP and DHCPv6 are inherited for the
      respective extensions, therefore relevant sections of <xref
      target="RFC4861" /> and <xref target="RFC3315" /> should be consulted.
      In any case, signaling addresses and prefixes to be special-purpose
      does not have a significant impact on the underlying assignment and
      delegation mechanisms.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>IANA is requested to setup a pvd DNS TXT Record Key registry
      with the initial types: <xref target="keys-services">s, z, 6, 4</xref>;
      <xref target="keys-dns">r, d</xref>; <xref target="keys-conn">bw, lt,
      rl, tm, cp, nat</xref> and a prefix <xref target="keys-private">x-
      </xref> for <xref target="RFC5226">Private Use</xref>. The policy
      for further additions to the registry is requested to be <xref
      target="RFC5226">RFC Required</xref>.</t>

      <t>This document defines a new bit for the NDP Prefix Information
      Option (the S-bit). There is currently no registration procedure for
      such bits, so IANA should not take any action on this matter.</t>

      <t>IANA should assign a DHCPv6 option code OPTION_SPECIAL_PURPOSE to
      the DHCPv6 option code space defined in <xref target="RFC3315" />.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6763.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2308.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3646.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6106.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7556.xml"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative references">
      <reference anchor="PEN" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/enterprise-numbers">
	<front>
	  <title>Private Enterprise Numbers</title>
	  <author><organization>IANA</organization></author>
	  <date />
	</front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="This solution compared to doing this in DHCPv6/NDP [RFC
                    Editor: please remove]">

      <t>The angle of attack of the MIF work to date (autumn 2015) has been
      to add container options and their transfer mechanisms to DHCPv6 and
      NDP. This document details a different approach, and therefore it is
      sensible to compare it to to the existing solutions in terms of
      (highly subjective) pros and cons.

      The authors consider pros of this proposal to be:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>No overhead for hosts that do not care (possibly most; no
        spurious RA options, ...)</t>

        <t>No problems with relaying data; if the first-hop device does not
        care, DNS requests propagate onward.</t>

        <t>Little/no changes to DHCP, DHCPv6, DHCPv6-PD or RA.</t>

        <t>No duplication of specifications / TLVs for DHCP, DHCPv6 and
        RA.</t>

        <t>Solves m:n prefix &lt;-&gt; PVD elegantly: no need to either
        duplicate applying prefix for each PVD or duplicate each PVD for
        each applying prefix.</t>

        <t>Easily extensible (TXT records, no TLV definitions, parsing and
        generation necessary)</t>

        <t>Probably not affected by IPR on draft-ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support</t>

        <t>Reuses the existing reverse DNS infrastructure</t>
      </list>

      The authors consider cons of this proposal to be:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>This scheme requires DNS servers ‘close’ on the path to the
        user, if changed information is to be sent; otherwise centralized
        solution would work (with some synthesized records).</t>

        <t>Security using either DNSSec or in-band hashes is rather painful
        (but possibly not more than the scheme in the current DHCP/RA
        drafts), so the default would most likely be insecure. That is not
        much different from DHCP*/RA, which are also 99.999…% of the time
        not secured.</t>

      </list>

      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Discussion Points [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>
    	<list style="symbols">
    	  <t>Besides special purpose prefixes, it might be desirable to
    	  have special purpose routers which only provide access to certain
    	  services but not the entire internet. These services could be
    	  announced by only using more-specific routes, however if the
    	  destination addresses are possibly changing, extension of the RIO
    	  mechanism might be needed. One possibility would be to add a new
    	  RIO S-flag with semantics like: "When the host receives a Route
    	  Information Option with the S-Bit set, it MUST ignore the value
    	  in the Prf-field (even if it is (10)) and instead assume the
    	  preference to have a value greater than (11). However, it MUST
    	  only use the route for packets having a source prefix announced
    	  by the same router.". This would allow selective routes
    	  (Prf=(10)) only applying to MIF-hosts.</t>

          <t>DNSSEC delegation of reverse zones might be difficult in some
          cases.  It is debatable, whether we want a complementary in-band
          signing mechanism as well, e.g., pre-shared public keys
          associated the domain name of the TXT records and "sig-X=..."
          keys (where X identifies the specific key) and ... is an
          EdDSA or ECDSA signature over all records not starting with
          "sig-". Care would need to be taken wrt. TTL and negative caching
          though.</t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Changelog [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>draft-stenberg-mif-mpvd-dns-00:
      <list style="symbols">

        <t>Initial version.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Draft Source [RFC Editor: please remove]">
      <t>As usual, this draft is available at <eref
      target="https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/">
      https://github.com/fingon/ietf-drafts/</eref>
      in source format (with nice Makefile too). Feel free to send comments
      and/or pull requests if and when you have changes to it! </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>Thanks to Eric Vyncke for the original idea of using DNS for
      transmitting PVD information.</t>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
